<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Graph vspacing="30" hspacing="200" padding="40" guid="B860474C-F01D-13B1-45B4-A83FBC7A126D"><Nodes><Node guid="679D3D7596D8" nodeName="National recognition of Heydar Aliyev" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="840" yPos="40" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">The tradition of giving grand and detailed speeches at various party congresses, forums and conferences arose in the post-Stalin era and flourished to hyperbolic extremes under Brezhnev. Despite illness and difficulties with his voice, Brezhnev was a prolific public speaker, and his addresses at party conferences could last almost a whole day. Party leaders throughout the union republics were also expected to speak publicly. They took their lead from the Kremlin. In the 1970s Baku hosted a huge number of events, and not only party functions: cultural days for various union republics; all-Union or international conferences, meetings of workers to mark Azerbaijan being given challenge red banners. Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking could be heard at all of these gatherings and forums. I was curious to investigate the preparation involved in his famous speeches and reports, especially as none of his biographers have ever investigated this. All party conferences and plenums in Baku were conducted in Russian, and the documents were then sent to Moscow. As an exception, sessions of the Supreme Soviet took place in Azerbaijani. Heydar Aliyev was bilingual and was able to switch freely between the two language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language.</data></Node><Node guid="0EA128079601" nodeName="Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="40" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Party leaders throughout the union republics were also expected to speak publicly. They took their lead from the Kremlin. In the 1970s Baku hosted a huge number of events, and not only party functions: cultural days for various union republics; all-Union or international conferences, meetings of workers to mark Azerbaijan being given challenge red banners. Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking could be heard at all of these gatherings and forums. I was curious to investigate the preparation involved in his famous speeches and reports, especially as none of his biographers have ever investigated this. All party conferences and plenums in Baku were conducted in Russian, and the documents were then sent to Moscow. As an exception, sessions of the Supreme Soviet took place in Azerbaijani. Heydar Aliyev was bilingual and was able to switch freely between the two language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language.</data></Node><Node guid="9458ADBECDD1" nodeName="Heydar Aliyev’s bilingual" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="70" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Party leaders throughout the union republics were also expected to speak publicly. They took their lead from the Kremlin. In the 1970s Baku hosted a huge number of events, and not only party functions: cultural days for various union republics; all-Union or international conferences, meetings of workers to mark Azerbaijan being given challenge red banners. Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking could be heard at all of these gatherings and forums. I was curious to investigate the preparation involved in his famous speeches and reports, especially as none of his biographers have ever investigated this. All party conferences and plenums in Baku were conducted in Russian, and the documents were then sent to Moscow. As an exception, sessions of the Supreme Soviet took place in Azerbaijani. Heydar Aliyev was bilingual and was able to switch freely between the two language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language.</data></Node><Node guid="48233EBA45C9" nodeName="Improvisation in Azerbaijani" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="100" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Party leaders throughout the union republics were also expected to speak publicly. They took their lead from the Kremlin. In the 1970s Baku hosted a huge number of events, and not only party functions: cultural days for various union republics; all-Union or international conferences, meetings of workers to mark Azerbaijan being given challenge red banners. Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking could be heard at all of these gatherings and forums. I was curious to investigate the preparation involved in his famous speeches and reports, especially as none of his biographers have ever investigated this. All party conferences and plenums in Baku were conducted in Russian, and the documents were then sent to Moscow. As an exception, sessions of the Supreme Soviet took place in Azerbaijani. Heydar Aliyev was bilingual and was able to switch freely between the two language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language.</data></Node><Node guid="1722476F8B8E" nodeName="Non-use of the pre-prepared text" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="115" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language.</data></Node><Node guid="EBBA1B3E7342" nodeName="As always he spoke simply and was easy to understand'" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="130" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language. The famous Azerbaijani writer Movlud Suleymanly recalls an occasion in the mid-1970s, just before New Year, when the entire city did voluntary work on a Saturday to lay the foundations of a park on Shikhov Beach. The Writer’s Union had their own section where these literary individuals planted trees. Aliyev strolled about the future park, chatting with people, before finally approaching the representatives of the creative intelligentsia. “As always he spoke simply and was easy to understand, recalls Suleymanly. “He joked with the ‘elder statesmen’ as well as showing an interest in the young writers.</data></Node><Node guid="44BFEE189674" nodeName="Memories of the poet Gabil" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="160" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">The poet Gabil noted rather frankly that Heydar Aliyevich spoke Azerbaijani really well. Heydar Aliyev began to laugh softly. ‘Gabil, it’s strange that you should be surprised that I speak Azerbaijani, but not by my knowledge of Russian. Azerbaijani is my mother tongue, I have a duty' to know it - and not just me, but all of us.” These words were met with applause. But the matter did not end there. The leader’s belief in the importance of knowing your native language spread to all corners of the republic very quickly, forcing bureaucrats to reconsider their disdain towards Azerbaijani. The words that Heydar Aliyev had spoken at an ordinary Saturday’s volunteering and his overall work in this area changed the cold attitude Azerbaijani society had previously shown towards its own language.</data></Node><Node guid="6A2CE3FF6C51" nodeName="Impeccable mother tongue skills" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="160" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">The poet Gabil noted rather frankly that Heydar Aliyevich spoke Azerbaijani really well. Heydar Aliyev began to laugh softly. ‘Gabil, it’s strange that you should be surprised that I speak Azerbaijani, but not by my knowledge of Russian. Azerbaijani is my mother tongue, I have a duty' to know it - and not just me, but all of us.” These words were met with applause. But the matter did not end there. The leader’s belief in the importance of knowing your native language spread to all corners of the republic very quickly, forcing bureaucrats to reconsider their disdain towards Azerbaijani. The words that Heydar Aliyev had spoken at an ordinary Saturday’s volunteering and his overall work in this area changed the cold attitude Azerbaijani society had previously shown towards its own language.</data></Node><Node guid="01371489B864" nodeName="Recognition" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="190" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In 1970 a group of prominent intellectuals asked Heydar Aliyev to attend a party meeting at the Azerbaijan State University. He promised to come to an election and report meeting at the end of the year. He kept his word. The assembly hall was packed. On that day he spoke to those academics for around three hours in the purest Azerbaijani. In fact, it was his first speech to the academic community to earn a ‘hurrah’ and shatter a number of myths: firstly, that he was really a Russian-speaker, and secondly that this KGB-trained first secretary had only superficial knowledge. The audience was struck by his grasp of the subjects he addressed, his deep understanding of the psychology and mentality' of intellectuals, his fresh ideas and reflections on the situation in education, and his strategies to develop it in the republic. This meeting fundamentally changed the scientific and creative intelligentsias
attitude towards him.</data></Node><Node guid="3412D605B415" nodeName="A Gifted Orator" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="640" yPos="205" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Party leaders throughout the union republics were also expected to speak publicly. They took their lead from the Kremlin. In the 1970s Baku hosted a huge number of events, and not only party functions: cultural days for various union republics; all-Union or international conferences, meetings of workers to mark Azerbaijan being given challenge red banners. Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking could be heard at all of these gatherings and forums. I was curious to investigate the preparation involved in his famous speeches and reports, especially as none of his biographers have ever investigated this. All party conferences and plenums in Baku were conducted in Russian, and the documents were then sent to Moscow. As an exception, sessions of the Supreme Soviet took place in Azerbaijani. Heydar Aliyev was bilingual and was able to switch freely between the two language. According to the practice of the day, he would give most of his speeches in Russian, although he would use Azerbaijani whenever possible. In addition, he almost never used a pre-prepared text, improvising in Azerbaijani instead; perhaps this was partially because it was difficult to find anyone who could help him write a speech in this language.</data></Node><Node guid="76F32F257C2E" nodeName="First speech to the academic community" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="205" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In 1970 a group of prominent intellectuals asked Heydar Aliyev to attend a party meeting at the Azerbaijan State University. He promised to come to an election and report meeting at the end of the year. He kept his word. The assembly hall was packed. On that day he spoke to those academics for around three hours in the purest Azerbaijani. In fact, it was his first speech to the academic community to earn a ‘hurrah’ and shatter a number of myths: firstly, that he was really a Russian-speaker, and secondly that this KGB-trained first secretary had only superficial knowledge. The audience was struck by his grasp of the subjects he addressed, his deep understanding of the psychology and mentality' of intellectuals, his fresh ideas and reflections on the situation in education, and his strategies to develop it in the republic. This meeting fundamentally changed the scientific and creative intelligentsias
attitude towards him.</data></Node><Node guid="77103D36C0B4" nodeName="Deep understanding of the psychology and mentality' of intellectuals" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="220" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In 1970 a group of prominent intellectuals asked Heydar Aliyev to attend a party meeting at the Azerbaijan State University. He promised to come to an election and report meeting at the end of the year. He kept his word. The assembly hall was packed. On that day he spoke to those academics for around three hours in the purest Azerbaijani. In fact, it was his first speech to the academic community to earn a ‘hurrah’ and shatter a number of myths: firstly, that he was really a Russian-speaker, and secondly that this KGB-trained first secretary had only superficial knowledge. The audience was struck by his grasp of the subjects he addressed, his deep understanding of the psychology and mentality' of intellectuals, his fresh ideas and reflections on the situation in education, and his strategies to develop it in the republic. This meeting fundamentally changed the scientific and creative intelligentsias
attitude towards him.</data></Node><Node guid="21534530BB58" nodeName="Rechecking personally by Aliyev his speeches" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="250" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Nevertheless, even with this final draft in hand, Heydar Aliyev would still improvise elements as he addressed a plenum or party activists - anything from a few phrases or paragraphs to entire pages. “Back then there were no voice recorders,” recalls Vladimir Morozkov. «So I sat near a loudspeaker in the wings and checked the prepared text against what Heydar Aliyev was actually saying. I made a note of any deviations, as I didn’t trust the stenographers. They tended to work slowly and didn’t give us their transcripts until later on. But we needed the corrections for the following day’s press. The main text of the speech was set beforehand, but would await correction towards evening. When we had made the necessary changes, we took our materials to Heydar Aliyevich. He examined the whole text yet again together with its additions and amendments. And then as late as 9, 10 or even 11 p.m. we would ‘chase’ the newspapers with our final version. He worked more meticulously than anyone else on official texts. He checked literally every word, every paragraph of information concerning
his work that would appear in print the next morning.” Zakir Abdullayev remembers: “I saw how Heydar Aliyevich would personally refine the documents his team had prepared. At the time, Yakov Kirsanov was head of the Central Committee’s General Department, and was an extremely intelligent man. However, the texts he produced were fundamentally reworked by Heydar Aliyevich, who would polish every fine detail. The paper would often be covered in notes on both sides. Aides may have drafted these texts, but Heydar Aliyevich was the master craftsman who revised everything from start to finish. He had the handwriting of a calligrapher, and it was a real pleasure to read the notes he made.” The majority of Heydar Aliyev’s speeches began with a tribute to the times, an expression of gratitude to the CPSU Central Committee and its trusted helmsman, or a declaration of belief in Lenin’s party and devotion to the struggle for a bright communist future. This was just the necessary preamble, however. The essence of a report was its critical content. I would say that Heydar Aliyev’s capacity for self-criticism was unmatched. “All of Heydar Aliyev’s speeches were written in a critical tone and set new tasks,” Hasan Seyidov remembers. ‘There were so many successes throughout the republic, all sectors of the national economy were growing, but still he was critical! The more things we found to criticise, the more negative points we put to him, the happier he was. I would sometimes suggest that we say a bit more about our successes. ‘No’, he’d answer, ‘we need to keep it brief when it comes to success.’ I would point out that our enemies would say we had been bragging about success, but then indicate how many failures we had had. He would reply that the more candid we were about our shortcomings,
the fewer there would be in future.”</data></Node><Node guid="2B5BD2DAC906" nodeName="The case of rewriting the report by Heydar Aliyev" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="280" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Zakir Abdullayev tells a similar story: “Heydar Aliyevich often said: ‘The key to success and development begins with critical analysis and exposing shortcomings. If you do not recognise your shortcomings, you will become self-satisfied and think that you have nothing to improve’." Turan Hüseynov recalls an occasions when professors were called in from Kirovabad to help the agricultural secretary write a speech for an upcoming plenum. “After Heydar Aliyev had received their preliminary work, he called in his assistant - I was there - and said: ‘What kind of report is this? It has been written by doctors of science, professors, but it doesn’t contain a single fresh fact!’ He tore the entire thing up and threw it in the bin. He then told me not to send anyone in - he did not want to be disturbed. He stayed in the office until morning rewriting the report. Through his various channels he enquired about matters in certain regions and discovered their unresolved issues, their weak spots. In Zardab Region, for example, it had rained, but the cotton had not been covered with cellophane and had begun to rot. They had been thrifty in Kurdamir, but not in Zardab or Aghdash. He gathered facts like these and brought them up at the plenum. Then the secretaries of the district committees called me and asked with fear and astonishment who had written the speech for him. ‘What do you mean?’ I replied. ‘Listen, those facts are brand new; we haven’t even reported them yet. Where could he have got that information?’ Heydar Aliyevich left no stone unturned, you see. He had evidently
learnt this in his previous job with the secret service, where mistakes could prove life-threatening.” Heydar Aliyev's speeches and discourses at less substantial events were pure improvisation. He would attend numerous meetings with part; members, workers or voters, and would bring only a short text that the departments had prepared. This would contain a few facts, outlines, talking points and statistics. He would “beef up” the text as he went along, turning it into a full speech. His peers relate that he would address active party functionaries for two to three hours, speaking mainly without notes. Many people still remember a brilliant speech Heydar Aliyev made
in The Gulustan Palace - which had only recently been opened - to celebrate 60 years of the Soviet Socialist Republic of Azerbaijan. Large delegations from all of the union republics were in attendance with their first secretaries. At this reception, Heydar Aliyev raised his glass in honour of each delegation in turn and gave a unique speech containing such exact information about the history, culture and traditions of each republic that all the attendees were simply shocked. He concluded by reciting a quatrain from the republic’s classic literature by heart. In the words of Svetlana Gasimova: “It was a shining demonstration of Heydar Aliyev’s phenomenal personality, his erudition and intellect. He spoke in the purest Russian, without any notes - it had to be heard to be believed!”</data></Node><Node guid="05958D3688A5" nodeName="Nerve centre of Heydar Aliyev" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="440" yPos="310" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Heydar Aliyev formed his own nerve centre, bringing in Azerinfonn Director Efim Gurvich, an aide to First Secretary Ramiz Tariverdiyev and Arif Mustafayev, Head of the General Department Yakov Kirsanov, and future Head of the Propaganda Department Afrand Dashdamirov to work on compiling his reports. From the outset, these men would gather in his office to discuss the subject matter and general concept of a report, its direction, key sections, highlights, and so forth. Then the appropriate department would issue a questionnaire, which would be used to compile extensive background information. The group would use this information to consolidate the text, putting it into the language of a report. Gurvich would then go through this rough draft and streamline it. Members of Heydar Aliyev’s team smiled as they told me how the secretaries from various district and municipal committees would make a pilgrimage to see Gurvich in the run-up to a plenum or congress. Some would ask him to lessen his criticism or remove their names from a report; others implored
him to note their “achievements” in one of its positive sections.
During this preparation, the material would be constantly refined and
polished, and fresh facts would be added. Of course, Heydar Aliyev would
examine the text extensively himself, contributing his own observations
and suggestions, personally re-writing and re-working the report anil
throwing up new ideas and thoughts. Central Committee secretaries and
the departments that came under their remit would also be involved.
The Central Committee Bureau members would receive the repor:
several days before the start of a plenum. They would gather for a
discussion and express their own wishes and observations. On Heydar
Aliyev’s suggestion, constructive observations would be added to the
speech’s final draft.</data></Node><Node guid="3AE8D9D39386" nodeName="The more candid we were about our shortcomings, the fewer there would be in future" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="310" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Nevertheless, even with this final draft in hand, Heydar Aliyev would still improvise elements as he addressed a plenum or party activists - anything from a few phrases or paragraphs to entire pages. “Back then there were no voice recorders,” recalls Vladimir Morozkov. «So I sat near a loudspeaker in the wings and checked the prepared text against what Heydar Aliyev was actually saying. I made a note of any deviations, as I didn’t trust the stenographers. They tended to work slowly and didn’t give us their transcripts until later on. But we needed the corrections for the following day’s press. The main text of the speech was set beforehand, but would await correction towards evening. When we had made the necessary changes, we took our materials to Heydar Aliyevich. He examined the whole text yet again together with its additions and amendments. And then as late as 9, 10 or even 11 p.m. we would ‘chase’ the newspapers with our final version. He worked more meticulously than anyone else on official texts. He checked literally every word, every paragraph of information concerning
his work that would appear in print the next morning.” Zakir Abdullayev remembers: “I saw how Heydar Aliyevich would personally refine the documents his team had prepared. At the time, Yakov Kirsanov was head of the Central Committee’s General Department, and was an extremely intelligent man. However, the texts he produced were fundamentally reworked by Heydar Aliyevich, who would polish every fine detail. The paper would often be covered in notes on both sides. Aides may have drafted these texts, but Heydar Aliyevich was the master craftsman who revised everything from start to finish. He had the handwriting of a calligrapher, and it was a real pleasure to read the notes he made.” The majority of Heydar Aliyev’s speeches began with a tribute to the times, an expression of gratitude to the CPSU Central Committee and its trusted helmsman, or a declaration of belief in Lenin’s party and devotion to the struggle for a bright communist future. This was just the necessary preamble, however. The essence of a report was its critical content. I would say that Heydar Aliyev’s capacity for self-criticism was unmatched. “All of Heydar Aliyev’s speeches were written in a critical tone and set new tasks,” Hasan Seyidov remembers. ‘There were so many successes throughout the republic, all sectors of the national economy were growing, but still he was critical! The more things we found to criticise, the more negative points we put to him, the happier he was. I would sometimes suggest that we say a bit more about our successes. ‘No’, he’d answer, ‘we need to keep it brief when it comes to success.’ I would point out that our enemies would say we had been bragging about success, but then indicate how many failures we had had. He would reply that the more candid we were about our shortcomings,
the fewer there would be in future.”</data></Node><Node guid="7EC229CD568F" nodeName="Citation" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="340" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Well-known sayings of Heydar Aliyev.</data></Node><Node guid="5F059D3CCE2B" nodeName="The key to success and development begins with critical analysis and exposing shortcomings" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="340" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Zakir Abdullayev tells a similar story: “Heydar Aliyevich often said: ‘The key to success and development begins with critical analysis and exposing shortcomings. If you do not recognise your shortcomings, you will become self-satisfied and think that you have nothing to improve’." Turan Hüseynov recalls an occasions when professors were called in from Kirovabad to help the agricultural secretary write a speech for an upcoming plenum. “After Heydar Aliyev had received their preliminary work, he called in his assistant - I was there - and said: ‘What kind of report is this? It has been written by doctors of science, professors, but it doesn’t contain a single fresh fact!’ He tore the entire thing up and threw it in the bin. He then told me not to send anyone in - he did not want to be disturbed. He stayed in the office until morning rewriting the report. Through his various channels he enquired about matters in certain regions and discovered their unresolved issues, their weak spots. In Zardab Region, for example, it had rained, but the cotton had not been covered with cellophane and had begun to rot. They had been thrifty in Kurdamir, but not in Zardab or Aghdash. He gathered facts like these and brought them up at the plenum. Then the secretaries of the district committees called me and asked with fear and astonishment who had written the speech for him. ‘What do you mean?’ I replied. ‘Listen, those facts are brand new; we haven’t even reported them yet. Where could he have got that information?’ Heydar Aliyevich left no stone unturned, you see. He had evidently
learnt this in his previous job with the secret service, where mistakes could prove life-threatening.” Heydar Aliyev's speeches and discourses at less substantial events were pure improvisation. He would attend numerous meetings with part; members, workers or voters, and would bring only a short text that the departments had prepared. This would contain a few facts, outlines, talking points and statistics. He would “beef up” the text as he went along, turning it into a full speech. His peers relate that he would address active party functionaries for two to three hours, speaking mainly without notes. Many people still remember a brilliant speech Heydar Aliyev made
in The Gulustan Palace - which had only recently been opened - to celebrate 60 years of the Soviet Socialist Republic of Azerbaijan. Large delegations from all of the union republics were in attendance with their first secretaries. At this reception, Heydar Aliyev raised his glass in honour of each delegation in turn and gave a unique speech containing such exact information about the history, culture and traditions of each republic that all the attendees were simply shocked. He concluded by reciting a quatrain from the republic’s classic literature by heart. In the words of Svetlana Gasimova: “It was a shining demonstration of Heydar Aliyev’s phenomenal personality, his erudition and intellect. He spoke in the purest Russian, without any notes - it had to be heard to be believed!”</data></Node><Node guid="06429B39B37E" nodeName="If you do not recognise your shortcomings, you will become self-satisfied and think that you have nothing to improve" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="370" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Zakir Abdullayev tells a similar story: “Heydar Aliyevich often said: ‘The key to success and development begins with critical analysis and exposing shortcomings. If you do not recognise your shortcomings, you will become self-satisfied and think that you have nothing to improve’." Turan Hüseynov recalls an occasions when professors were called in from Kirovabad to help the agricultural secretary write a speech for an upcoming plenum. “After Heydar Aliyev had received their preliminary work, he called in his assistant - I was there - and said: ‘What kind of report is this? It has been written by doctors of science, professors, but it doesn’t contain a single fresh fact!’ He tore the entire thing up and threw it in the bin. He then told me not to send anyone in - he did not want to be disturbed. He stayed in the office until morning rewriting the report. Through his various channels he enquired about matters in certain regions and discovered their unresolved issues, their weak spots. In Zardab Region, for example, it had rained, but the cotton had not been covered with cellophane and had begun to rot. They had been thrifty in Kurdamir, but not in Zardab or Aghdash. He gathered facts like these and brought them up at the plenum. Then the secretaries of the district committees called me and asked with fear and astonishment who had written the speech for him. ‘What do you mean?’ I replied. ‘Listen, those facts are brand new; we haven’t even reported them yet. Where could he have got that information?’ Heydar Aliyevich left no stone unturned, you see. He had evidently
learnt this in his previous job with the secret service, where mistakes could prove life-threatening.” Heydar Aliyev's speeches and discourses at less substantial events were pure improvisation. He would attend numerous meetings with part; members, workers or voters, and would bring only a short text that the departments had prepared. This would contain a few facts, outlines, talking points and statistics. He would “beef up” the text as he went along, turning it into a full speech. His peers relate that he would address active party functionaries for two to three hours, speaking mainly without notes. Many people still remember a brilliant speech Heydar Aliyev made
in The Gulustan Palace - which had only recently been opened - to celebrate 60 years of the Soviet Socialist Republic of Azerbaijan. Large delegations from all of the union republics were in attendance with their first secretaries. At this reception, Heydar Aliyev raised his glass in honour of each delegation in turn and gave a unique speech containing such exact information about the history, culture and traditions of each republic that all the attendees were simply shocked. He concluded by reciting a quatrain from the republic’s classic literature by heart. In the words of Svetlana Gasimova: “It was a shining demonstration of Heydar Aliyev’s phenomenal personality, his erudition and intellect. He spoke in the purest Russian, without any notes - it had to be heard to be believed!”</data></Node><Node guid="DE94A4B8F64E" nodeName="Armenians' failed attempt to seize Nagorno-Karabakh in the mid-1960s" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="400" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In addition to questions of economics and politics, his opposition to Armenian separatism, which he had experienced at first hand, was one of Heydar Aliyev’s enduring concerns during his time as the first secretary, especially at the beginning. I have described his work relating to this issue while he was head of the KGB at length in the first part of this book. Heydar Aliyev was confronted with this emerging separatism as soon as he was elected first secretary. After the Armenians had made the typical failed attempt to seize Nagorno-Karabakh in the mid-1960s, they changed tactics and embraced a less aggressive policy playing dirty tricks on their neighbours. They dragged out some old maps from the late 1920s, declared some land on che Azerbaijani border to be “Armenian since rime immemorial" and demanded that it should be ceded to Armenia. “The talks lasted two or three years,” Aliyev recalled much later. “They were led not only by Veli Akhundov but also by Mammad Isgandarov, Enver Alikhanov, and the second secretary, Elistratov. Unfortunately, in 1969, these talks resulted in a decision by the .Azerbaijan Supreme Soviet that these borderlands did, indeed, belong to Armenia and should be given back. When I became the leader of Azerbaijan in the July of that year, I mulled over the problem for a month and finally refused to implement the ruling. They continued to push for the question to be resolved in their favour for a long rime, but I resisted. I understand how this unfair decision was made at that time. There is no longer any need to discuss that, but I would like to stress that Veli Akhundov had absolutely no desire to hand over these pieces of land. It was only pressure from Moscow and other sources that made such a decision unavoidable."  In an interview with the journalist Elmira Ahmadova, Heydar Aliyev recalled that: “In September 1969, I called the first secretary' of Armenia, Anton Kochinyan, and requested a meeting. Our meeting took place on the border between the Gazakh [Azerbaijan] and Ijevan [Armenia) districts. 1 put the issue firmly on the table and suggested that Kochinyan should take concrete measures to counter the territorial pretensions of Armenian nationalists. In my opinion, it was a productive meeting, because there was no further trouble whatsoever between our two countries in the ensuing period."-’ In his book Sem Pisem v Irevan [Seven letters to Irevan), the famous Azerbaijani poet, writer and publisher Hidayat writes: “In one of the interviews, possibly the last, published in the youth magazine Garun in 1988, the former Armenian leader, Anton Kochinyan, said that during his leadership, the Karabakh ‘question’ was brought up on several occasions, but Heydar Aliyev’s authority and the weight his opinion held in Moscow prevented it from being ‘resolved’. Mikhail Suslov went as far as to summon Kochinyan and insist ‘enough Armenian nationalism!’ That put an end to the ‘Karabakh problem’ during the Brezhnev years. It could well be for this reason that Brezhnev’s demise was seen in Yerevan as good news.”</data></Node><Node guid="DA72544885F0" nodeName="Some land on the Azerbaijani border to be “Armenian since time immemorial&quot;" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="400" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">There were nevertheless a host of unpleasant incidents at the beginning of the 1970s. One of these incidents, provoked by Armenian nationalists, took place in 1969 in the settlement of Bayan, in Azerbaijan’s Dashkasan District. People from Bayan, who were living in Yerevan and other Soviet cities, decided to erect a memorial obelisk there at their own expense to commemorate local casualties of the Second World War in perpetuity. Committees were organised in Moscow, Baku, Kirovabad, Khanlar and other Soviet cities to raise funds for the construction of the monument. Some 22,000 roubles were collected and spent on the construction of the sculpture in Yerevan. It took the form of a I4-inetre obelisk of grey basalt, with a sculpted three-metre high eagle on its main face and a weeping woman in bas-relief on one of the side faces.
Remembering this episode, which had taken place almost 40 years before, the academician, Omar Eldarov, explained to me the true significance of die image of the eagle on the sculpture:
“This eagle was in fact a copy of one of the most important details on a monument in Yerevan honouring the victory of the Armenians over the lurks in the Batdc of Sardarabad,” he explained. “There are two anti¬Turkish monuments in Yerevan. One is a monument to the victims of genocide and the other, a monument adorned with eagles and huge bulls, celebrates the Armenian victory in the Battle of Sardarabad. The eagle was an exact copy of a fragment from that monument, only much smaller.”</data></Node><Node guid="086020B07364" nodeName="Die image of the eagle on the sculpture" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="430" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">There were nevertheless a host of unpleasant incidents at the beginning of the 1970s. One of these incidents, provoked by Armenian nationalists, took place in 1969 in the settlement of Bayan, in Azerbaijan’s Dashkasan District. People from Bayan, who were living in Yerevan and other Soviet cities, decided to erect a memorial obelisk there at their own expense to commemorate local casualties of the Second World War in perpetuity. Committees were organised in Moscow, Baku, Kirovabad, Khanlar and other Soviet cities to raise funds for the construction of the monument. Some 22,000 roubles were collected and spent on the construction of the sculpture in Yerevan. It took the form of a I4-inetre obelisk of grey basalt, with a sculpted three-metre high eagle on its main face and a weeping woman in bas-relief on one of the side faces.
Remembering this episode, which had taken place almost 40 years before, the academician, Omar Eldarov, explained to me the true significance of die image of the eagle on the sculpture:
“This eagle was in fact a copy of one of the most important details on a monument in Yerevan honouring the victory of the Armenians over the lurks in the Batdc of Sardarabad,” he explained. “There are two anti¬Turkish monuments in Yerevan. One is a monument to the victims of genocide and the other, a monument adorned with eagles and huge bulls, celebrates the Armenian victory in the Battle of Sardarabad. The eagle was an exact copy of a fragment from that monument, only much smaller.”</data></Node><Node guid="12FE4C1421BB" nodeName="Spontaneous demonstration" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="430" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">There were nevertheless a host of unpleasant incidents at the beginning of the 1970s. One of these incidents, provoked by Armenian nationalists, took place in 1969 in the settlement of Bayan, in Azerbaijan’s Dashkasan District. People from Bayan, who were living in Yerevan and other Soviet cities, decided to erect a memorial obelisk there at their own expense to commemorate local casualties of the Second World War in perpetuity. Committees were organised in Moscow, Baku, Kirovabad, Khanlar and other Soviet cities to raise funds for the construction of the monument. Some 22,000 roubles were collected and spent on the construction of the sculpture in Yerevan. It took the form of a I4-inetre obelisk of grey basalt, with a sculpted three-metre high eagle on its main face and a weeping woman in bas-relief on one of the side faces.
Remembering this episode, which had taken place almost 40 years before, the academician, Omar Eldarov, explained to me the true significance of die image of the eagle on the sculpture:
“This eagle was in fact a copy of one of the most important details on a monument in Yerevan honouring the victory of the Armenians over the lurks in the Batdc of Sardarabad,” he explained. “There are two anti¬Turkish monuments in Yerevan. One is a monument to the victims of genocide and the other, a monument adorned with eagles and huge bulls, celebrates the Armenian victory in the Battle of Sardarabad. The eagle was an exact copy of a fragment from that monument, only much smaller.” The members of the Regional Committee Bureau discussed the issue and decided to remove the sculpture of the eagle from the monument. During die night of the 25th July, without the prior knowledge of the residents, it was removed and taken away. This act provoked outrage amongst the villagers and a stream of letters and telegrams flooded into the Soviet and Azerbaijani patty organs. In addition, emissaries arrived from Yerevan deliberately to inflame the situation. They claimed that the action of the regional authorities had denigrated the memory of the fallen. Local residents held a spontaneous demonstration and hurled insults and threats against the party leadership and Soviet district authorities. The chairman of the collective farm belonging to the settlement of Bayan and the secretary of the party organisation were branded as traitors and threatened with physical violence. A commission was dispatched as a matter of urgency from Baku under the leadership of the secretary to the Communist Party, Ali Amirov, who was sent to brief the local population.</data></Node><Node guid="5E2764325966" nodeName="A host of unpleasant incidents in 1970s" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="440" yPos="445" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In addition to questions of economics and politics, his opposition to Armenian separatism, which he had experienced at first hand, was one of Heydar Aliyev’s enduring concerns during his time as the first secretary, especially at the beginning. I have described his work relating to this issue while he was head of the KGB at length in the first part of this book. Heydar Aliyev was confronted with this emerging separatism as soon as he was elected first secretary. After the Armenians had made the typical failed attempt to seize Nagorno-Karabakh in the mid-1960s, they changed tactics and embraced a less aggressive policy playing dirty tricks on their neighbours. They dragged out some old maps from the late 1920s, declared some land on che Azerbaijani border to be “Armenian since rime immemorial" and demanded that it should be ceded to Armenia. “The talks lasted two or three years,” Aliyev recalled much later. “They were led not only by Veli Akhundov but also by Mammad Isgandarov, Enver Alikhanov, and the second secretary, Elistratov. Unfortunately, in 1969, these talks resulted in a decision by the .Azerbaijan Supreme Soviet that these borderlands did, indeed, belong to Armenia and should be given back. When I became the leader of Azerbaijan in the July of that year, I mulled over the problem for a month and finally refused to implement the ruling. They continued to push for the question to be resolved in their favour for a long rime, but I resisted. I understand how this unfair decision was made at that time. There is no longer any need to discuss that, but I would like to stress that Veli Akhundov had absolutely no desire to hand over these pieces of land. It was only pressure from Moscow and other sources that made such a decision unavoidable."  In an interview with the journalist Elmira Ahmadova, Heydar Aliyev recalled that: “In September 1969, I called the first secretary' of Armenia, Anton Kochinyan, and requested a meeting. Our meeting took place on the border between the Gazakh [Azerbaijan] and Ijevan [Armenia) districts. 1 put the issue firmly on the table and suggested that Kochinyan should take concrete measures to counter the territorial pretensions of Armenian nationalists. In my opinion, it was a productive meeting, because there was no further trouble whatsoever between our two countries in the ensuing period."-’ In his book Sem Pisem v Irevan [Seven letters to Irevan), the famous Azerbaijani poet, writer and publisher Hidayat writes: “In one of the interviews, possibly the last, published in the youth magazine Garun in 1988, the former Armenian leader, Anton Kochinyan, said that during his leadership, the Karabakh ‘question’ was brought up on several occasions, but Heydar Aliyev’s authority and the weight his opinion held in Moscow prevented it from being ‘resolved’. Mikhail Suslov went as far as to summon Kochinyan and insist ‘enough Armenian nationalism!’ That put an end to the ‘Karabakh problem’ during the Brezhnev years. It could well be for this reason that Brezhnev’s demise was seen in Yerevan as good news.”</data></Node><Node guid="DB4A17BBBA3D" nodeName="Act of terrorism in 1973" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="460" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Barely two years later, the Armenian nationalists carried out an even deadlier act of terrorism, on this occasion in the capital of the Soviet Union. In 1973, three explosions rocked Moscow, one in a shop on 25th October Street (now Nikolskaya Street), one in Derzhinsky Square and one on the underground between Izlaimovsky Park and Pervomaiskaya. 29 people lost their lives as a result of these attacks. The talc of the painstaking investigation and search for the terrorists is covered in Filipp Bobkov’s book KGB i Vhst [The KGB and power]. Tiny fragments were pieced together to recreate first the container that had held the explosive (a casserole dish) and then the device placed on the underground. The passengers who had been in the carriage when the device went off were located and helped to put together a description of people who had left the carriage at stations before the tragedy took place. The descriptions proved conclusive: there were two terrorists, and it transpired that both were Armenian. Staff working at the Operational Investigation Unit met every plane and train arriving in Yerevan from Moscow and additional searches were carried out elsewhere. Two men matching the description of those seen at the Kursk train station emerged from the very first train to arrive in Yerevan from Moscow. They were Stepanyan and Bagdasaryan, members of an illegal nationalist group under the leadership of a certain Zatikyan. When his home was searched a casserole dish identical to the one that exploded on the underground was discovered in his attic. After their arrest, the perpetrators were confronted with the casserole dish that had been reassembled from fragments as well as various other pieces of physical evidence. “It turned out,” writes Filipp Bobkov, “that all three were members of an illegal nationalist party opposed to the Soviet system, and consequently, Moscow. They had decided to wreak revenge on the Russians: women, children, old people, it didn’t matter who so long as they were Russian. Such an incident should have attracted the attention of party and government officials and encouraged them to seek ways in which to address the causes of this interethnic hatred. However, apart from the investigative and legal procedures in Moscow, there were no repercussions. The Armenian authorities did everything they could to keep the crime from the general population. Karen Demirchyan, the first secretary of the CPA Central Committee, banned all Armenian newspapers from publishing information concerning the act of terrorism. A documentary on the trial of Zatikyan and his fellow conspirators, filmed during the High Court sessions, was banned from being shown even to prominent members of the Armenian communist party, and was viewed only by a narrow circle of the highest officials. Neither was the film shown in cinemas, despite the considerable advantages it would have had and the contribution it would have made in terms of awareness building. The Armenian leadership justified the ban by claiming that they wished to avoid compromising the Armenian people in the eyes of the Russians ... Nobody wanted to draw political conclusions from the facts of the attack ... The authorities in the capital and elsewhere seemed not to realise that the problem would not stop there. Even some years later, when nationalist tendencies were beginning to grow and the Dashnaks were resolutely spreading their ideological beliefs in Armenia, the local authorities refused to counter these movements, evidently not by accident.”</data></Node><Node guid="18665E4443C1" nodeName="Petition asking for the settlement of the following issues" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="490" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">As a result, the residents were promised a new memorial, which was to be placed upon the monument with their agreement and at the government’s expense. The project was entrusted to the Council of Artists of the Republic, who were to create a sculpted figure to reflect the tragedy of the fallen soldiers. Yet another shocking incident took place in the summer of 1969. Its instigators hoped to whip up tensions and whip up suspicion between the Armenians and the Azerbaijanis. On IS* August 1969, at Ararat train station in the Armenian Soviet  Socialist Republic, a group of Armenian hooligans maliciously attacked the conductors on a train on the 257 Yerevan — Baku route. The acting chairman of the Azerbaijan branch of the KGB, Vitaly Krasilnikov, describes this crime in a letter addressed to Heydar Aliyev, stating that, “a large crowd of riotous individuals from amongst the local population gathered at the station during the incident and created a disturbance.”
In the late 1960s and early 1970s, Armenian separatists attempted to foist the so-called “Kurdish problem” onto the Azerbaijani authorities, with the intention of causing trouble.
In a letter addressed to Heydar Aliyev (10/1522, 29"' October 1969) on the subject, the chairman of the Azerbaijan branch of the KGB, Vitaly Krasilnikov, writes that:
“According to information received by us, Kurds living in the Armenian SSR are intending to send a delegation to the Azerbaijani authorities with a petition asking for the settlement of the following issues:
1. To permit the Kurds living in the Armenian, Turkmenistan and Kyrgyzstan Soviet Socialist Republics to emigrate to the Azerbaijani SSR and to allocate a separate autonomous territory for them (?!);
2. To open schools with teaching in Kurdish;
3. lo create favourable conditions for the publication of creative, scientific and other literature in the Kurdish language;
4. lo publish newspapers and broadcast radio programmes in Kurdish in the territory allocated to the Kurds;
5. To show concern for the provision of suitable employment for the Kurdish intelligentsia.”</data></Node><Node guid="C881B89AAA8E" nodeName="An ethnic cleansing of Kurds" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="520" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">As a result, the residents were promised a new memorial, which was to be placed upon the monument with their agreement and at the government’s expense. The project was entrusted to the Council of Artists of the Republic, who were to create a sculpted figure to reflect the tragedy of the fallen soldiers. Yet another shocking incident took place in the summer of 1969. Its instigators hoped to whip up tensions and whip up suspicion between the Armenians and the Azerbaijanis. On IS* August 1969, at Ararat train station in the Armenian Soviet  Socialist Republic, a group of Armenian hooligans maliciously attacked the conductors on a train on the 257 Yerevan — Baku route. The acting chairman of the Azerbaijan branch of the KGB, Vitaly Krasilnikov, describes this crime in a letter addressed to Heydar Aliyev, stating that, “a large crowd of riotous individuals from amongst the local population gathered at the station during the incident and created a disturbance.”
In the late 1960s and early 1970s, Armenian separatists attempted to foist the so-called “Kurdish problem” onto the Azerbaijani authorities, with the intention of causing trouble.
In a letter addressed to Heydar Aliyev (10/1522, 29"' October 1969) on the subject, the chairman of the Azerbaijan branch of the KGB, Vitaly Krasilnikov, writes that:
“According to information received by us, Kurds living in the Armenian SSR are intending to send a delegation to the Azerbaijani authorities with a petition asking for the settlement of the following issues:
1. To permit the Kurds living in the Armenian, Turkmenistan and Kyrgyzstan Soviet Socialist Republics to emigrate to the Azerbaijani SSR and to allocate a separate autonomous territory for them (?!);
2. To open schools with teaching in Kurdish;
3. lo create favourable conditions for the publication of creative, scientific and other literature in the Kurdish language;
4. lo publish newspapers and broadcast radio programmes in Kurdish in the territory allocated to the Kurds;
5. To show concern for the provision of suitable employment for the Kurdish intelligentsia.”</data></Node><Node guid="631A2A72A443" nodeName="“Kurdish problem”" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="440" yPos="550" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">The Armenian nationalists, thus, resolved to carry out an ethnic cleansing of Kurds from their territory under the cover of a touching “concern” for their national and cultural rights. It is odd, though, that the idea of Kurdish autonomy on their own soil did not occur to them. In his book Intcrvyu s Generalom Razvedki [An Interview with a general from the intelligence services], Ilhuseyn Huseynov writes:
“The 1970s were characterised by the brazen manner in which Armenian nationalists would raise the question of the ‘historic possession of the Karabakh territory by Armenia.’ The key players in these ‘activities’ came from the intelligentsia and youth, whose actions were coordinated by nationalist circles in Yerevan. They shifted their tactics to the stockpiling of weapons and military equipment, distributed pamphlets and attempted to form underground nationalist youth groups in order to achieve their criminal aims. It was precisely during this period that the Azerbaijan branch of the KGB managed to expose a certain R. Danelyan and the members of his terrorist group who threw a grenade amongst a group of Azerbaijanis in Stepanakert in June, 1971.”’</data></Node><Node guid="99EB805DAE01" nodeName="An Interview with a general from the intelligence services" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="550" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">The Armenian nationalists, thus, resolved to carry out an ethnic cleansing of Kurds from their territory under the cover of a touching “concern” for their national and cultural rights. It is odd, though, that the idea of Kurdish autonomy on their own soil did not occur to them. In his book Intcrvyu s Generalom Razvedki [An Interview with a general from the intelligence services], Ilhuseyn Huseynov writes:
“The 1970s were characterised by the brazen manner in which Armenian nationalists would raise the question of the ‘historic possession of the Karabakh territory by Armenia.’ The key players in these ‘activities’ came from the intelligentsia and youth, whose actions were coordinated by nationalist circles in Yerevan. They shifted their tactics to the stockpiling of weapons and military equipment, distributed pamphlets and attempted to form underground nationalist youth groups in order to achieve their criminal aims. It was precisely during this period that the Azerbaijan branch of the KGB managed to expose a certain R. Danelyan and the members of his terrorist group who threw a grenade amongst a group of Azerbaijanis in Stepanakert in June, 1971.”’</data></Node><Node guid="3601018AE509" nodeName="Armenian Separatism" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="640" yPos="565" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In addition to questions of economics and politics, his opposition to Armenian separatism, which he had experienced at first hand, was one of Heydar Aliyev’s enduring concerns during his time as the first secretary, especially at the beginning. I have described his work relating to this issue while he was head of the KGB at length in the first part of this book. Heydar Aliyev was confronted with this emerging separatism as soon as he was elected first secretary. After the Armenians had made the typical failed attempt to seize Nagorno-Karabakh in the mid-1960s, they changed tactics and embraced a less aggressive policy playing dirty tricks on their neighbours. They dragged out some old maps from the late 1920s, declared some land on che Azerbaijani border to be “Armenian since rime immemorial" and demanded that it should be ceded to Armenia. “The talks lasted two or three years,” Aliyev recalled much later. “They were led not only by Veli Akhundov but also by Mammad Isgandarov, Enver Alikhanov, and the second secretary, Elistratov. Unfortunately, in 1969, these talks resulted in a decision by the .Azerbaijan Supreme Soviet that these borderlands did, indeed, belong to Armenia and should be given back. When I became the leader of Azerbaijan in the July of that year, I mulled over the problem for a month and finally refused to implement the ruling. They continued to push for the question to be resolved in their favour for a long rime, but I resisted. I understand how this unfair decision was made at that time. There is no longer any need to discuss that, but I would like to stress that Veli Akhundov had absolutely no desire to hand over these pieces of land. It was only pressure from Moscow and other sources that made such a decision unavoidable."  In an interview with the journalist Elmira Ahmadova, Heydar Aliyev recalled that: “In September 1969, I called the first secretary' of Armenia, Anton Kochinyan, and requested a meeting. Our meeting took place on the border between the Gazakh [Azerbaijan] and Ijevan [Armenia) districts. 1 put the issue firmly on the table and suggested that Kochinyan should take concrete measures to counter the territorial pretensions of Armenian nationalists. In my opinion, it was a productive meeting, because there was no further trouble whatsoever between our two countries in the ensuing period."-’ In his book Sem Pisem v Irevan [Seven letters to Irevan), the famous Azerbaijani poet, writer and publisher Hidayat writes: “In one of the interviews, possibly the last, published in the youth magazine Garun in 1988, the former Armenian leader, Anton Kochinyan, said that during his leadership, the Karabakh ‘question’ was brought up on several occasions, but Heydar Aliyev’s authority and the weight his opinion held in Moscow prevented it from being ‘resolved’. Mikhail Suslov went as far as to summon Kochinyan and insist ‘enough Armenian nationalism!’ That put an end to the ‘Karabakh problem’ during the Brezhnev years. It could well be for this reason that Brezhnev’s demise was seen in Yerevan as good news.”</data></Node><Node guid="9C6B2D625EC0" nodeName="Excerpt from the 1972 report of the KGB Division of the Nagorno- Karabakh Autonomous Regio" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="580" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Excerpt from the 1972 report of the KGB Division of the Nagorno- Karabakh Autonomous Region (the NKAR): “On 18lh June 1971 a hand grenade exploded outside the Karabakh Hotel, seriously injuring five Azerbaijanis. One of them later died of injuries sustained in the attack. Eight Armenians were subsequently arrested after investigations by the regional directorate of internal affairs and a special unit from the garrison at Stepanakert.  A large  collection of weapons and military equipment was uncovered during a search of their homes. Head of Division Bystrov.”At first, the office of the public prosecutor of the NKAR led the investigation into the explosion. Then it was taken over by the Ministry of Internal Affairs of the NKAR. One of the ringleaders was arrested and later freed, ostensibly due to lack of evidence against him, but more than likely due to pressure from local inhabitants. Over a period of several months, six volumes full of information were compiled, but the investigation had reached an impasse. Heydar Aliyev examined the case at the Central Committee Bureau and decided to hand the investigation over to the “committee officials”. The matter of the grenade was, therefore, left in the hands of our old acquaintance, Akram Selimzadeh.</data></Node><Node guid="DA41F99EB61C" nodeName="Akram Selimzadeh’s story" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="580" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">From Akram Selimzadeh’s story: “ ... I asked the leader of our department to provide me with translators who would translate all the relevant documents from Azerbaijani and Armenian into Russian. Since the matter revolved almost entirely around Armenian nationals, I suggested that an Armenian speaker should be included in our team of investigators. I was given Safar Aliyev. He had lived in Armenia and completed his education in Armenian. I was also given Sasha Shkitov as an investigator. The translators got down to business the very next morning. They translated all the material relating to the investigation and I then realised that it would be possible to throw light on the incident. There had simply been no system to the enquiries up to that point. It is quite possible that the Armenians had not read what the Azerbaijanis wrote, and vice versa. We made progress. Soon we arrested Eduard ‘Pshka’ Danelyan, Valeri Agadzhanyan and Slavik Agadzhanyan. A total of eight people were arrested in connection with the investigation. Valeri Agadzhanyan was the first to be arrested. When we examined the case materials we discovered that, when he was talking to his fellow conspirators, he had declared, ‘ You threw the grenade among the Azerbaijanis in vain.’ There is a hotel called ‘Karabakh’ in Stepanakert. All the PE teachers from the schools in the nearby regions - including Fuzuli and Shusha - had been invited to a seminar there. A large group of young Azerbaijanis had gathered in the evening and were chatting at the entrance to the hotel. Their only crime was their Azerbaijani nationality. The Armenians, who had managed to steal an RG-42 hand grenade from a military post, were concealed behind the hotel building and threw the grenade amongst the Azerbaijanis from there. One died immediately, another had to have his legs amputated and the rest were also wounded. We succeeded in ‘breaking’ Valeri Agadzhanvan. After all, the very exclamation: ’You threw the grenade among the .Azerbaijanis in vain’, provided us with a way in. Valeri gave us all the details and named the perpetrators. He himself was amongst them and had been present when the act of terrorism was being planned; it had been Eduard Danelyan who convinced them to go ahead with it. ‘Let’s throw a grenade,’ he urged his fellow conspirators, ‘let’s blow up some Azerbaijanis, Turks that they are. We’ll have our revenge.’</data></Node><Node guid="346F316406C1" nodeName="Intensifying of nationalist atmosphere" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="240" yPos="610" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Heydar Aliyev understood better than anyone the danger of an intensifying nationalist atmosphere amongst the party nomenclature of the NKAJR. He resolved, for this reason, to bolster the leadership of the autonomous region with trusted and dependable staff. In the autumn of 1973, he put forward the then first secretary of the Kirovsky District Party in Baku, Boris Kevorkov, for election as first secretary of the CPA Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee. A plenum of the CPA Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee took place on October 12th, 1973. The Committee relieved Gurgen Melkumyan of his duties as first secretary and took away his membership of the Bureau of the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee and elected Kevorkov in his place. Melkumyan was subsequendy employed at the Azerbaijani Trade Union Council.-’ Heydar Aliyev held Boris Kevorkov in high regard, petitioned for him to be awarded the Order of Lenin and two Orders of the Red Banner of Labour and put him forward for election to the Supreme Soviet. Kevorkov was also a candidate for membership of the CPA Central Committee Bureau. It is of note that Boris Kevorkov worked as first secretary right up until 23"1 February 1988, when he was relieved of his duties by a plenum of the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee “for inadequacies in the workplace”. The undercover millionaire and staunch separatist, Genrikh Pogosyan, took his place. In 1975, at a plenum of the regional party committee, the first secretary of the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee, criticised the nationalist elements who were striving to undermine political stability in Nagorno- Karabakh. Boris Kevorkov listed concrete facts and names, including that of Zoriy Balayan, and condemned attempts to turn the Dashnakist, Andronik, into a national hero. Heydar Aliyev described the consequences of that speech as follows:“The nationalists reared their ugly heads once again and incited all sorts of acts of provocation against the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee, especially Boris Kevorkov. Telegrams were sent to .Moscow and other regions and tensions increased. Two months later we met Karen Demirchyan in Moscow and talked to him for four hours. I made it abundantly clear to him that any problems at all in the NKAR were to be resolved by the regional authorities and the leadership of Azerbaijan. Any interference in Karabakh by others could well damage our transnational relations, something that we could not allow. The situation was stable once again.”’</data></Node><Node guid="05A1A36E73C9" nodeName="The change of the leadership of the autonomous region" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="610" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Heydar Aliyev understood better than anyone the danger of an intensifying nationalist atmosphere amongst the party nomenclature of the NKAJR. He resolved, for this reason, to bolster the leadership of the autonomous region with trusted and dependable staff. In the autumn of 1973, he put forward the then first secretary of the Kirovsky District Party in Baku, Boris Kevorkov, for election as first secretary of the CPA Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee. A plenum of the CPA Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee took place on October 12th, 1973. The Committee relieved Gurgen Melkumyan of his duties as first secretary and took away his membership of the Bureau of the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee and elected Kevorkov in his place. Melkumyan was subsequendy employed at the Azerbaijani Trade Union Council.-’ Heydar Aliyev held Boris Kevorkov in high regard, petitioned for him to be awarded the Order of Lenin and two Orders of the Red Banner of Labour and put him forward for election to the Supreme Soviet. Kevorkov was also a candidate for membership of the CPA Central Committee Bureau. It is of note that Boris Kevorkov worked as first secretary right up until 23"1 February 1988, when he was relieved of his duties by a plenum of the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee “for inadequacies in the workplace”. The undercover millionaire and staunch separatist, Genrikh Pogosyan, took his place. In 1975, at a plenum of the regional party committee, the first secretary of the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee, criticised the nationalist elements who were striving to undermine political stability in Nagorno- Karabakh. Boris Kevorkov listed concrete facts and names, including that of Zoriy Balayan, and condemned attempts to turn the Dashnakist, Andronik, into a national hero. Heydar Aliyev described the consequences of that speech as follows:“The nationalists reared their ugly heads once again and incited all sorts of acts of provocation against the Nagorno-Karabakh Regional Committee, especially Boris Kevorkov. Telegrams were sent to .Moscow and other regions and tensions increased. Two months later we met Karen Demirchyan in Moscow and talked to him for four hours. I made it abundantly clear to him that any problems at all in the NKAR were to be resolved by the regional authorities and the leadership of Azerbaijan. Any interference in Karabakh by others could well damage our transnational relations, something that we could not allow. The situation was stable once again.”’</data></Node><Node guid="D5DC3BC0AE50" nodeName="Citation in interview with Andrei Karaulov" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="640" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">In an interview with Andrei Karaulov, Heydar Aliyev described the positive indicators of socio-economic development in the NKAR during the 1970s and 1980s, and listed everything that had been achieved in Nagorno- Karabakh during his leadership: “A railway to the centre of the region, a wonderful train station in Stepanakert, a new airport. We organised regular flights between Stepanakert, Baku and Yerevan. I telephoned Karen Dcmirchyan and we agreed that Aeroflot Azerbaijan and Aeroflot Armenia would both operate the flights; you can see how we arranged all this down to the very last detail. Large- scale industries were built: a shoe factory, an electro-technical factory, factories producing condensers for the electronics industry and agricultural machinery etc. Significant measures were also undertaken to promote agriculture in the region. Two reservoirs were built with hydroelectric power stations as well as irrigation canals, which considerably improved water supply in the two regions. The production of grapes grew from 50¬60 thousand tonnes at the beginning of the 1970s to 120-130 thousand by 1980. Production associated with livestock farming nearly doubled. This is saying a lot for a small region with a population of 170,000. Much was achieved to promote social wellbeing. We founded a pedagogical institute in Stepanakert. It may not have been strictly necessary in such a small region, but we were hoping to co-operate with the intelligentsia. Lessons were taught in Armenian. I have already mentioned the construction of homes, schools, and health centres. We also restored and equipped the theatre and I supervised the construction of a large Palace of Political Enlightenment personally. We put up new monuments and we even rebuilt a large church that had once stood in Shusha and was destroyed in 1918, inviting stonemasons from Armenia to complete the work. We encouraged cultural relations between the NKAR and Armenia to flourish. Heads of ministries and departments and official bodies, theatre groups and concert bands, artists and academics frequently visited the autonomous region from Armenia. The slightest mention of any sort of restriction is entirely unfounded.”  Heydar Aliyev visited Nagorno-Karabakh twice a year in order to keep his finger on the pulse, and he received an ecstatic welcome every time.</data></Node><Node guid="01D155780143" nodeName="Heydar Aliyev’s conversation with Aleksandr Ivanov" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="670" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">Once the first secretary s car just could not make it up the hill into Shusha. He had arrived for the unveiling of a monument to Vagif. The automatic car, a Zil, stalled on the ascent from Stepanakert into Shusha. Heavy snow had been falling since morning, all the paths to the mausoleum had disappeared under snowdrifts and the car began to slow down. It was then that local residents, many of whom were Armenian, lifted it up and carried it for some time, rescuing it from sinking into the snow. That shows how much they thought of him.” However, the more Heydar Aliyev achieved in Nagorno-Karabakh, the more he was disliked in certain Armenian circles, that is to say, among those who were determined to appropriate this bountiful little comer of Azerbaijan. There are a number of interesting facts concerning this in Hidayat's book, Seven Letters to Yerevan:
“Before the Azerbaijani leader became a member of the country’s senior leadership, there were always images of all the members and candidates for membership of the CPSU Central Committee Politburo dotted round Yerevan. However, this came to an end with the election of Heydar Aliyev, so that they did not have to display his portrait at festivities and demonstrations. I recall that, in the autumn of 1976, a meeting was held at the Yerevan Pedagogical Institute between Vardges Petrosyan, H. Emin and myself. As I was coming up the stairs to the last floor where the assembly hall was located, I saw portraits of all the members and candidates for membership of the Politburo on a stand. I came, first of all, to the conclusion that the students in the Azerbaijani sector, situated opposite the assembly hall, had taken care of this. But the place where Heydar Aliyev’s portrait should have been was empty. Perplexed, I turned to the dean of the Languages and Literature Faculty and asked him indignantly why the portrait had been taken down. The dean replied, hesitating, ‘Yes ... Someone’s pinched it ... We’ll find another portrait just the same.’
I didn’t have dme to react to this ‘explanation’ before we were invited into the assembly hall and all quickly took our seats for the presidium. But this upsetting incident had left a bad taste in my mouth. The rector declared the meeting open and after having had a word with Vardges Petrosyan, he put the microphone aside, turned to me and said, ‘Don’t be upset about the portrait, it’s just some idiot’s prank.’ Clearly, he’d heard my question addressed to the dean when we were coming up the stairs. ‘I’ll deal with it personally. We’ll find a portrait of the same size and fix it in place.’
‘Some idiot’s prank’ seemed to me a funny way of putting it. I replied, ‘Mikoyan’s portrait has hung above our heads in Azerbaijan for 30 years, but not a single Azerbaijani has made so bold as to tear it down. Do you really think that we don’t have any idiots among us Azerbaijanis? But even so, nobody’s ever done anything like this.’ The rector turned red in the face, was going to say something in reply, but stopped short and instead muttered something to himself.”  Hidayat recalls that, on more than one occasion when he was travelling round Armenia, he came across portraits of Heydar Aliyev that had been defaced by vandals, "My driver Hamlet, an Armenian by birth, would tear down the defaced portraits while cursing his fellow countrymen and, mad with rage, would take them back to the car.”   
Heydar Aliyev was on friendly terms with Marshal Baghramyan. Heydar Alivev saw the Second World War as sacred, and he had the greatest respect for those who had contributed to the overthrow of Hitler’s Third Reich. Every year on May 9,h he would meet veterans of the Great Patriotic War without fail, present them with commemorative gifts and awards and make sure that all their social needs and problems were attended to.
When Marshal Baghramyan was awarded the title of Hero of the Soviet Union for the second time, the question of a statue in his homeland was brought up. He was bom in the mountain village of Chardakhly in the Shamkhor (now Shamkir) region of Azerbaijan, but, in Hidyat’s words: "He failed to tell the truth about his early life and, in his personal records, identified his place of birth not as the village of Chardakhly, but the city of Ganja (previously named Yelisavetpol, and Kirovabad in Soviet times). This false information consequently appeared in reference books and encyclopaedias. The only connection that the future marshal had with Ganja was that he had studied at the technical college there.”</data></Node><Node guid="D1E562A51A41" nodeName="The later statements made by the Heydar Aliyev regarding the “Armenian issue”" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="700" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">“I was the first secretary of the CPA Central Committee from 14'h July 1969 to 3ri December 1982, said Heydar Aliyev, “and during the whole of that period not an inch of Azerbaijani territory was conceded to Armenia although Armenia made a number of attempts to take land from us. That’s a fact. They never spoke about this openly, but the need to redefine the maps of Azerbaijan and Armenia was brought to my attention. This was because certain mistakes had been made during the 1920s. I replied that our borders were defined, and there was no need whatsoever to change anything.
I seem to remember that some gold mines were opened on the border of the Kalbajar region. The Armenians crossed over to our side and began exploratory survey operations there. When I found out, I instructed the Council of Ministers and the leadership of the Kalbajar region to expel them from our lands forthwith.”Both at the start of the Nagorno-Karabakh conflict and afterwards, Heydar Aliyev was convinced that this issue was not conceived in the NKAR itself: “I visited the NKAR on a number of occasions,” he recounted at a later date, “toured extensively in the region and conversed at length with the Armenians living there. Not one of them breathed a word about handing Karabakh over to Armenia. I remember one more thing. We were marking the 50* anniversary of the NKAR. When the region was awarded the Order of Peoples’ Friendship, I gave a speech at the ceremony, and there is one sentence from that speech for which the Armenian nationalists cannot forgive me to this day. I detected a certain mood and I said, ‘The Nagorno-Karabakh Autonomous Region is an inseparable part of Azerbaijan, and will remain so now and forever more.’”-’</data></Node><Node guid="0049BC30F153" nodeName="Conversation with the former chairman of the Azerbaijan Supreme Court Ibrahim Ismayilov" nclass="" shape="circle" xPos="40" yPos="730" color="13421772"><data tclass="" link="" type="text">“I arrived for a reception with Heydar Aliyev in the summer of 1982 and said that we needed to do something about the Armenian nationalists, that they were totally out of hand, and that we ought to take the necessary measures. He replied, ‘But you know what goes on in Moscow, what influential forces they have behind them. If I could, I would do everything to stop them. But I don’t have the option’. He was a candidate for membership of the Politburo and close to Leonid Brezhnev, and yet he was unable to counter Armenian extremism. In 1983, two students from El Salvador were lolled in Baku. Three people were connected to the case, two main perpetrators and a third who helped cover up the crime. The organiser was an Armenian called Spartak Akopyan. He was sentenced to the maximum punishment, the death penalty, and was shot. The other two were sentenced to lengthy terms of imprisonment. It was a very high-profile case and was given wide coverage on television. In the Zavokzalnaya district of Baku, people said that the punishment was too severe and that Akopyan could have been pardoned. I was presiding over the court, since I was chairman of the Azerbaijan Supreme Court of Azerbaijan at that time. In 1984 five Armenians were caught trying to cross the Nakhchivan border illegally. Iwo were shot by border guards and the remaining three were detained and tried in court. I presided over the court hearing, but it was the Azerbaijani prosecutor-general, Abbas Zamanov, who was in charge of the prosecution. The culminating story is one of fraud and embezzlement, the protagonists of which were the crooks, Dadamyan and Bagdasaryan. Bagdasaryan had already been tried in court before. Since they were clandestine millionaires, they were able to buy off the press, the Union Prosecution Service, and leading members of our government. They must have spent a fortune in Moscow. Enver Gafarov presided over the trial, and was made to suffer for his integrity; he was offered large sums of money, and ultimately given the boot for convicting them. He was unemployed for several years. The Soviet deputy prosecutor-general submitted a protest, and the judicial division of the Soviet Supreme Court brought the case back. It continued for two years without making any progress, was then handed over to the office Soviet prosecutor-general and, eventually, found its way to our public prosecution office with instructions to carry out the investigation procedure for a second time. Ultimately, the case was reclassified under Article 167 and “played down”. All these cases were seen in Moscow as being politically motivated. They caused a stir and were hilled as the organised persecution and victimisation of Armenians. People were outraged that the judicial system in Azerbaijan repressed people on account of their national origins. They started to see me as an enemy of the Armenian people, Heydar AJiyevs man and one who would supposedly continue his tough stance against the Armenians. So, they forced me out too. All in all, in the late 1970s and early 1980s, the unimaginable began to happen. There was an immediate problem if there were Armenians among the criminals being convicted of a crime. It only took one of them to be convicted and an order would come through for the sentence either to be either revoked or amended to a milder one from the Soviet prosecutor-general’s office, where a former resident of Baku worked, a certain Mizaryan. Moreover, big money was involved. We’re talking about bribery and corruption. But even if bribes were taken here, then it was only to the tunc of 1,000 or 2,000 roubles, whereas in the central law- enforcement agencies, we are talking of millions. Overall, I’m convinced that Heydar Aliyev was sent to Moscow not because they just loved him so much, but in order to solve the Armenian issue’ here and give them Karabakh.”</data></Node></Nodes><Edges><Edge guid="68E608CA7FAF" group="" node1="A Gifted Orator" node2="National recognition of Heydar Aliyev"/><Edge guid="CB617BB47259" group="" node1="Armenian Separatism" node2="National recognition of Heydar Aliyev"/><Edge guid="A6DE224BA84D" group="" node1="Improvisation in Azerbaijani" node2="Non-use of the pre-prepared text"/><Edge guid="1D24D9C040FF" group="" node1="As always he spoke simply and was easy to understand'" node2="Non-use of the pre-prepared text"/><Edge guid="CE10FC430C4B" group="" node1="Impeccable mother tongue skills" node2="Memories of the poet Gabil"/><Edge guid="816D3C2588A5" group="" node1="Heydar Aliyev’s brilliant and sharp speaking" node2="A Gifted Orator"/><Edge guid="A86FEEF960CB" group="" node1="Heydar Aliyev’s bilingual" node2="A Gifted Orator"/><Edge guid="0FF3F525492D" group="" node1="Non-use of the pre-prepared text" node2="A Gifted Orator"/><Edge guid="4E80B0683C94" group="" node1="Memories of the poet Gabil" node2="A Gifted Orator"/><Edge guid="479DDA1FB652" group="" node1="First speech to the academic community" node2="A Gifted Orator"/><Edge guid="867AC1AFF8DF" group="" node1="Nerve centre of Heydar Aliyev" node2="A Gifted Orator"/><Edge guid="2EC1436A8ADB" group="" node1="Recognition" node2="First speech to the academic community"/><Edge guid="AB63FC0BBC8D" group="" node1="Deep understanding of the psychology and mentality' of intellectuals" node2="First speech to the academic community"/><Edge guid="C904D0C2AFC4" group="" node1="Rechecking personally by Aliyev his speeches" node2="Nerve centre of Heydar Aliyev"/><Edge guid="A00E6F4413B6" group="" node1="The case of rewriting the report by Heydar Aliyev" node2="Nerve centre of Heydar Aliyev"/><Edge guid="88DA72390C09" group="" node1="Citation" node2="Nerve centre of Heydar Aliyev"/><Edge guid="8392520CF90C" group="" node1="The more candid we were about our shortcomings, the fewer there would be in future" node2="Citation"/><Edge guid="DF40F1BBDEFF" group="" node1="The key to success and development begins with critical analysis and exposing shortcomings" node2="Citation"/><Edge guid="66CDD6946DE0" group="" node1="If you do not recognise your shortcomings, you will become self-satisfied and think that you have nothing to improve" node2="Citation"/><Edge guid="4BED56442892" group="" node1="Some land on the Azerbaijani border to be “Armenian since time immemorial&quot;" node2="Armenians' failed attempt to seize Nagorno-Karabakh in the mid-1960s"/><Edge guid="F511AFE935A4" group="" node1="Spontaneous demonstration" node2="Die image of the eagle on the sculpture"/><Edge guid="8F8AC8AED065" group="" node1="Die image of the eagle on the sculpture" node2="A host of unpleasant incidents in 1970s"/><Edge guid="EF4D8FD7D2E3" group="" node1="Act of terrorism in 1973" node2="A host of unpleasant incidents in 1970s"/><Edge guid="DC968CBDC654" group="" node1="Petition asking for the settlement of the following issues" node2="“Kurdish problem”"/><Edge guid="35700E78A7A5" group="" node1="An ethnic cleansing of Kurds" node2="“Kurdish problem”"/><Edge guid="642515B1EB0E" group="" node1="An Interview with a general from the intelligence services" node2="“Kurdish problem”"/><Edge guid="59A27310E948" group="" node1="Excerpt from the 1972 report of the KGB Division of the Nagorno- Karabakh Autonomous Regio" node2="“Kurdish problem”"/><Edge guid="854D8837E70D" group="" node1="Intensifying of nationalist atmosphere" node2="“Kurdish problem”"/><Edge guid="2A434E001192" group="" node1="Armenians' failed attempt to seize Nagorno-Karabakh in the mid-1960s" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="FD25FCB10B24" group="" node1="A host of unpleasant incidents in 1970s" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="42EE66C940D7" group="" node1="“Kurdish problem”" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="415EC7A2C63F" group="" node1="Citation in interview with Andrei Karaulov" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="E1659DFA7DD3" group="" node1="Heydar Aliyev’s conversation with Aleksandr Ivanov" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="B0211D1AA68B" group="" node1="The later statements made by the Heydar Aliyev regarding the “Armenian issue”" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="8D0856E46691" group="" node1="Conversation with the former chairman of the Azerbaijan Supreme Court Ibrahim Ismayilov" node2="Armenian Separatism"/><Edge guid="5D39AFD8C808" group="" node1="Akram Selimzadeh’s story" node2="Excerpt from the 1972 report of the KGB Division of the Nagorno- Karabakh Autonomous Regio"/><Edge guid="38617CF463CE" group="" node1="The change of the leadership of the autonomous region" node2="Intensifying of nationalist atmosphere"/></Edges><Groups/></Graph>